Guide to the Bernard F. Burgunder Collection of George Bernard Shaw, [ca. 1810]-1990.
Bernard F. Burgunder Collection of George Bernard Shaw, [ca. 1810]-1990.
- Series IV. Outgoing Correspondence
  - 1908 -1915
    - GBS: Typed Letter [copy] to Augustin Hamon, Mar.3, 1908; 2 leaves + 3 leaves + 8 leaves (Box 11, Folder 2)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; My dear Hamon/ I telegraphed yesterday to same time. [Shaw discusses foreign language publications of his works. Included in folder is a 3 page explanation by B.F. Burgunder of the French & German editions of Shaw in the Cornell collection along with 8 pages of various catalogues listing Shaw items along with photocopies of some of the items listed. The Hamon letter is probably one of the items that was singled out.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Unknown, Mar.31, 1908; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 3)
      Ayot St. Lawrence: Dear Sir/ The story about the watch was in full swing about Charles Bradlaugh
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to Mrs. Eveleen Myers, Apr.27, 1908; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 4)
      London; Dine? Never.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to [Robert d'Humieres], May 3, 1908; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 5)
      Battler's Green, Letchmore Heath; My dear Marquis/ You are wrong about Hamon. He has style, grit,
    - GBS: Typed Letter [copy?] to Dr. Erich Hoffmann, May 12, 1908; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 6)
      [n.p.] Dear Sir, I am much obliged to you for your letter of the 26th inst.,
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to C. H. Norman, May 15, 1908; 1 leaf +1 leaf + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 7)
      London; My dear Norman, I have nothing whatever to say about the criticisms. With copy send by Guy Bolton to Shaw who returned it with a note: "Dear Guy Bolton/ I have no recollection of this letter ... [With catalogue listing of the letters upon which B.F. Burgunder has typed a long note.]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Miss Andrews, May 15, 1908; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 8)
      London; Dear Miss Andrews, In case you have been able to get Messrs Ellis and Walery
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Miss Marion Chappell, Oct.12, 1908; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 9)
      London; Dear Miss Chappell, It would of course be impossible for me to refuse to allow Richard Strauss
    - GBS: Typed Letter [copy] to Curt Otto, Oct.24, 1908; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 10)
      [n.p.] Dear Doctor Otto, Your letter of the 11th August arrived here while I was travelling abroad
    - GBS: Typed Letter [copy] to Curt Otto, Nov.12, 1908; 2 leaves + 1 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      [n.p.] Dear Doctor Otto, If the Creator of the Universe, surrounded by all his archangels, [With 1 leaf from Dan H. Laurence commenting on the Dr. Otto letters.]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to The Cambridge [Mass.] University Press, Nov.27, 1908; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      London; Dear Sirs, Enclosed is a preface for which I wish to secure American copyright. [With Dan H. Laurence's comments.]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Mrs. Gamble, Feb.2, 1909; 2 leaves + envelope (Box 11, Folder 13)
      London; My dear Mrs. Gamble, The difficulty in this religious controversy
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [fragment] Signed to Brentano's, Mar.20, 1909; 1 envelope (Box 11, Folder 14)
      Gibraltar; P.S. I hope this is sufficiently stamped. [Written on the envelope, no letter included.]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Augusta, Lady Gregory, Jun.12, 1909; 3 leaves + envelope (Box 11, Folder 15)
      London; Dear Lady Gregory, I think the best thing to do is to collect Synge's work first
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [copy] Signed to C.A. Vanderwell & Co., Nov.4, 1909; 2 leaves + 1 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      [n.p.] Dear Sirs/I have now carried my trial of your electric lighting system [With note from B.F. Burgunder and Dan H. Laurence]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Mona Limerick, Nov.13, 1909; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 17)
      London; Dear Miss Mona Limerick, In September last I wrote to your unworthy husband
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Augusta, Lady Gregory, Nov.6, 1909; 2 leaves + envelope (Box 11, Folder 18)
      London; Dear Lady Gregory, The Stage Society will take anything you can give it
    - GBS: Written Letter Signed to John E. Vedrenne, Dec. 16, 1909; 1 leaf + typed description (Box 11, Folder 18A)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; My Dear VD, Vex not your soul with the superman
    - GBS: Autgraph Letter Signed to James Waters, Jr., Jan.5, 1910; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 19)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; Dear Waters/ It is arranged that nothing is to come out about the repertory scheme
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to A. B. Kershaw, Jan.7, 1910; 1 leaf + envelope + 1 (Box 11, Folder 20)
      Queen's Hotel, Soutsea; Dear Sir, Your letter has only just overtaken me, [With not from dealer Paul C. Richards regarding the letter.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to A. B. Kershaw, Jan.20, 1910; 1 leaf + envelope + 1 (Box 11, Folder 21)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; Dear Sir/ I hope the enclosed will provide Miss Gladys with a satisfactory pet, [With note from B.F. Burgunder.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to John E. Vedrenne, Jan.11, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 22)
      London; If Miss Buona Bent will call tomorrow between 12.30 & 1,
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to John E. Vedrenne, Apr.6, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 23)
      Pyrenees; I shall not be back until the end of the month
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to C. H. Norman, Jun.3, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 24)
      London; I answered both letters. Have my replies miscarried?
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Unknown, Jul14, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 25)
      Ayot St. Lawwrence; Lord bless her innocence, with her two dozen!
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Robert Rattray, Jul.21, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 26)
      Edstaston wem Shrewsbury; I am afraid I am already full up for next season.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to John E. Vedrenne, Jul.21, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 27)
      Edstaston wem Shrewsbury; Whitney-Barbara is all bunkum. He wants to conciliate me
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to Ben Iden Payne, Jul.28, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 28)
      Carrigart Co., Donegal; It would be an interesting experiment: try it by all means.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [copy] Signed to Olga Nethersole, Sept.18, 1910; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 29)
      Parknasilla-on-Sea, Co. Kerry; My dear Miss Nethersole/ I shall never get this dreadful book out:
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to H. W. Massingham, Dec.16, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 30)
      Loondon; Mark anything on the proof you want softened or omitted.
    - GBS: AL [postcard] S to John E. Vedrenne, Dec.22, 1910; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 31)
      London; Barker won't come up: he syas that as the scenery is going into your store
    - GBS: Autograph Letters[postcards] to Margaret Halstan, May 18, 1911; 10 leaves + 10 leaves + 1 (Box 11, Folder 32)
      London; 10 directional postcards for Raina in "Arms and the Man". [Shaw apparently dropped in on the performance and noted his suggestions for her portrayal. Each postcard has a different picture of Shaw on the back. Plus there are transcriptions of each postcard on separate sheets. Plus a note from B.F. Burgunder explaining the situation.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [postcard] Signed to John E. Vedrenne, Jul.29, [1911]; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 33)
      Savoie, Thonon-les-Bains; I have no objection in the world to Mrs. Fay
    - GBS: Typed Letter [carbon] Signed to Ralph Brodrick, Nov.17, 1911; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 34)
      London; Dear Sir, I attach a special value to the invitation with which you have honored me
    - GBS: Typed Letter [mimeograph] to Emil Davies, Dec.13, 1911; 5 leaves (Box 11, Folder 35)
      London; My dear Emil Davies, In reply to your letter asking for my opinion [Note at top of letter says this letter was mimeographed and sent to all members of the Fabian Society.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Viola Tree, Dec.17, 1911; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 36)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; My dear Viola/ If I had had a notion that you would have liked Eurdice,
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to D. Lewin Mannering, Jan.2, 1912; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 37)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; Dear Lewin Mannering, You will drive me out of my senses.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Viola Tree, Jan.5, 1912; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 11, Folder 38)
      Edsteston wem Shrewsbury; My dear Viola/ Just three lines in frantic haste to catch the post.
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to John Palmer, Feb.24, 1912; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 39)
      London; Dear Mr. Palmer, What I said about a book on the censorship would not hold
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [shorthand draft] to J.N. Duddington, [Jun., 1912]; 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 40)
      [Ayot St. lawrence] Dear Mr. Duddington, Shall we say provisionally a pound a week for the furniture [With letter from Duddington to Mrs. Shaw, 23-6-12, and a transcription of Shaw's shorthand; plus a note from B.F. Burgunder with explanations.]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to C. H. Norman, Jun.25, 1912; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 41)
      [London] Dear Norman, The Malatesta Case comes sufficiently within the range of Radical interest [With note in Shaw's hand at the tope]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[postcard] Signed to Dorothy Minto, Jul.2, 1912; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 42)
      London; As the book is coming to pieces I have sent it to be stitched [With note from B. F. Burgunder giving background.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter [card] Signed to [Cyril Sykes], Oct.2, 1912; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 43)
      It is quite a mistake to suppose that male polictical prisoners are in any way privileged.
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Simon Brentano, Nov.6, 1912; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 44)
      London; My dear Mr. Brentano, Whatever the reason may be, it is beyond all question
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[card] to Simon Brentano, Nov.15, 1912; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 45)
      London; The enclosed will help to document my letter
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Augusta, Lady Gregory, Nov.18, 1912; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 46)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; My dear Lady Gregory/ Three times at least I have begun letters to you; [With comments from Dan. H. Laurence]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[postcard] Signed to Augusta, Lady Gregory, Nov.19, 1912; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 47)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; Our letters crossed. I'll write to the Lord Mayor. [Shaw photo on the back of the postcard]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Walter Stephens, Dec.11, 1912; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 48)
      London; Dear Sir, The thing is entirely impossible.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Blake Adams, Jan.1, 1913; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 11, Folder 49)
      London; Dear Blake Adams/ I made one or two notes at the last perfomance.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[postcard] Signed to William Poel, Jan.1, 1913; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 50)
      London; I was in front on Tuesday with Barker,
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Brentano's, Apr.19, 1913; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 51)
      London; Dear Brentanos, On going through your accounts I find no mention
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[postcard] Signed to Clifford Sharp, May 19, 1913; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 52)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; I have been finally crushed by Mrs. Patrick Campbell,
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Ashley Dukes, Jun.17, 1913; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 53)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; Dear Ashley Dukes/ It will perhaps amuse you to learn that the following conversation [With transcription included.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Rosina Fillippi, Sept.16, 1913; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 54)
      Valence -s-Rhone; My dear Rosina Filippi/ Thank you for a very welcome letter.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[postcard] Signed to Clifford Sharp, Nov.3, 1913; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 55)
      London; G.K.C. has utterly failed to get a rise out of me.
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to John E. Vedrenne, Nov.17, 1913; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 56)
      London; My dear Vedrenne, Have you got the old prompt copy of the Philanderer?
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[card] Signed to Unknown, [ca.1914-15]; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 57)
      London; Keep all these press cuttings until the performances [With note from B.F. Burgunder]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[postcard] Signed to Gilbert Murray, Feb.2, 1914; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 58)
      London; Sheafs of invitations, mostly from people who make downstrokes
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Fanny [Brough], Jun.16, 1914; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 59)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; Dearest Fanny/ What! Carlotta Addison gone! [With dealer's description with transcription included .]
    - GBS: Typed Letter[copy] Signed to Constable & Co., Nov., 1914; 1 leaf + 1 + 1 (Box 11, Folder 60)
      London; Dear Contables: My novels are not copywrite in America, [With letter from Constable & Co., November 10th 1914 asking Shaw about selling his books in America. Plus note from B.F. Burgunder on the copy and note from Dan H. Laurence too.]
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed to Bretano's, Nov.20, 1914; 4 leaves (Box 11, Folder 61)
      London; My dear Brentano's/ Mr Doubleday's offer is an important one.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[card] Signed to Harold Wright, Dec.11, 1914; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 11, Folder 62)
      London; Many thanks for the book. It will be most useful to me.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to W. Perriton Maxwell, Aug.9, 1915; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 63)
      Torquay; Dear Mr. Perriton Maxwell/ I had rather not answer your questions just now,
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Sir John Squire, Sept.1, 1915; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 64)
      orquay; Dear Squire/ Read the enclosed. Denis Mackail is a son of Jack Mackail [With note from B.F. Burgunder with brief identity sketches of those mentioned in the letter. Pasted into a hard binding.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Augusta, Lady Gregory, Sept.14, 1915; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 65)
      Torquay; My dear Lady Gregory/ O'Flaherty V.C. many now, I think, re regarded as a certainty.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[telegram] to Carolos Paton Blacker, Oct.4, 1915; 2 leaves (Box 11, Folder 66)
      Torquay; At vane Gower yesterday. Carolos handed the telegram from authorities.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to August, Lady Gregory, Oct.19, 1915; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 67)
      Torquay; My dear Lady Gregory/ On the point of returning to London
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Carlos Paton Blacker, Oct.19, 1915; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 68)
      Torquay; My dear Pep/ The worst is over at Vane Lower.
    - GBS: Autograph Letter[postcard] Signed to Carlos Paton Blacker, Oct.20, 1915; 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 69)
      Torquay; My letter of yesterday needs a postscript.
    - GBS: Autograph[shorthand] Letter Signed to Harry M. Paull, Oct.28, 1915; 2 leaves + 1 leaf (Box 11, Folder 70)
      [London] My dear Paull, The members present did me a great injustice. [With typed transcription of shorthand.]
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed to Florence (Johnston) Gamble, Nov.30, 1915; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 11, Folder 71)
      London; My dear Florence/ Why doesn't Constance get a war job? [With note from B.F. Burgunder]
  - 1916-1920
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Florence (Johnston) Gamble, Jan. 6, 1916; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 1)
      London?; begins "My dear Florence / How did that come about, I wonder?"
    - GBS: Typed Letter: to Brentano's, Jan. 15, 1916; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 2)
      London; begins "Dear Brentano's / I enclose, first, some photographs"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Brentano's, Feb. 18, 1916; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      London; with a typed prospectus; revised in Shaw's hand, for the volume of plays containing Androcles, Overruled, and Pygmalion
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Brentano's, Feb. 24, 1916; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 4)
      London; begins "Dear Brentanos / The shortage of labor here makes it"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], June 14, 1916; 2 leaves + envelope (Box 12, Folder 5)
      London; begins "Dear Hesketh Pearson / If you won't read my works by degrees"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson, Aug. 15, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 6)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; postcard bearing photograph of Shaw; begins "I sent the last copy but one of the Caesar / prologue"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Brentano's, Aug. 22, 1916; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 7)
      London; begins "Dear Brentanos / In your last accounting to me"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Augusta, Lady Gregory, Aug. 22, 1916; 3 leaves (Box 12, Folder 8)
      London; begins "My dear Lady Gregory / I have at last heard from Robert"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Augusta, Lady Gregory [initialed], Sept. 3, 1916; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 12, Folder 9)
      Sedbergh; begins "My dear Lady Gregory / I don't at all agree about Ibsen"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Augusta, Lady Gregory [initialed], Sept. 3, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 10)
      Sedbergh; begins "What are the prospects of the / Abbey Players ever"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson, Sept. 4, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      Sedbergh; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "I got Harris's book (the Wilde / one) before the 7th August"
    - GBS: Autograph Note: to "Carbonato" [Paul Reynolds], ca. Sept. 5, 1916; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Text of a telegram Shaw sent to his New York agent regarding the sale of O'Flaherty V.C.; with transcription on a separate leaf; begins "Am doubtful about Flaherty / What does Hearst offer / play contains roughly 9,000 words"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to John E. Vedrenne, Sept. 6, 1916; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Turners Hill, Sussex; purchased at Sotheby's, December 13, 1994; begins "I have been out of London since Androcles appeared"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson, Sept. 7, 1916; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 12, Folder 14)
      Sedbergh; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "Dear Hesketh Pearson / I have kept a copy of the letter"
    - GBS: Autograph Note: Envelopes addressed to Ernest Newman, the music critic, Aug.? and Sept. 13, 1916; envelope; 2 items (Box 12, Folder 15)
      One envelope is labelled Sedbergh, the other London
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Ernest Newman, Sept. 13, 1916; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 16)
      Sedbergh; begins "Dear Mr. Newman / I have just read your article"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Sept. 13, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      Sedbergh; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "I now find that there is a / difficulty about publication."
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Ernest Newman, Sept. 20, 1916; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 12, Folder 18)
      London; begins "My dear Newman / I cannot make up my mind about Glastonbury."
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson, Oct. 1, 1916; 1 leaf + 1 + envelope (Box 12, Folder 19)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "Now, God help you, you are, like all hero"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Oct. 3, 1916; 2 leaves + 2 + envelope (Box 12, Folder 20)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; typed transcription on separate leaf; with two of Shaw's printed postcards, one beginning "I have received your letter," the other beginning "Mr. Bernard Shaw's secretary has general instructions"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson, Oct. 20, 1916; 3 leaves + envelope (Box 12, Folder 21)
      London; begins "Dear Hesketh Pearson / Since you like writing letters"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to W.J. Bassett-Lowke, Nov. 1, 1916; postcard; 1 item + 1 (Box 12, Folder 22)
      London; the body of the letter is in the hand of Ann Elder, Shaw's secretary; includes note on separate leaf by Bernard Burgunder; begins "It is quite clear that there has been no advance on"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Nov. 10, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 23)
      London; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "Yes: my last letter to F.H. dealt with / Captain Kidd"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Dec. 7, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 24)
      London; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "If you have any copies of the Wilde book to / spare"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Dec. 13, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 25)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "I am sending one of my vellum copies"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Brentano's, Dec. 15, 1916; 2 leaves (Box 12, Folder 26)
      London; begins "Dear Brentanos / I have just come across an unanswered letter"
    - GBS: to Autograph Letter Signed: Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Dec. 22, 1916; 1 leaf + envelope (Box 12, Folder 27)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "You will see by the enclosed that / MacCarthy"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to A.G.? Gardiner, Dec. 28, 1916; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; with explanatory note on separate leaf; deals with World War I; begins "My dear Gardiner / I was, as you may imagine, delighted with your article: "The Dynasts"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to C.D. Medley, Jr. [initialed], Dec. 29, 1916; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 29)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; begins "Many thanks for the tip. I knew about the / section, and, as I now find on working out a few cases, / underrated its value."
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Augusta, Lady Gregory [initialed], Jan. 22, 1917; 3 leaves + envelope (Box 12, Folder 30)
      London; begins "My dear Lady Gregory / I have talked to the Stage Society"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Feb. 12, 1917; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 12, Folder 31)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "Dear Hesketh Pearson / I have been at the front"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Herbert Thurston, Feb. 22, 1917; 3 leaves + 15 (Box 12, Folder 32)
      London; with photocopy of Thurston's article "Truth and falsehood about crime in Germany" from The Month(London) Jan. 1916, pp. 19-33; begins "Dear Sir / I am greatly obliged to you for sending me your"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Hesketh Pearson [initialed], Mar. 26, 1917; postcard; 1 leaf + 1 (Box 12, Folder 33)
      Ayot St. Lawrence; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "If you will send me the article I / will try to"
    - GBS: Typed Letter Signed: to Augusta, Lady Gregory [initialed], May 4, 1917; 2 leaves + envelope (Box 12, Folder 34)
      London; begins "My dear Lady Gregory, I have practically pledged myself"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Lt. W.J. Wills, May 28, 1917; postcard; 1 item + 1 (Box 12, Folder 35)
      London; with typed transcription on separate leaf; begins "Dear Mr. Wills / How do you feel about it generally?"
    - GBS: Typed Letter: to Sergei Ivanov, June 21, 1917; carbon copy; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 36)
      Gift of Dan H. Laurence, January 1989; acquired by him as a discard from the British Museum; see his letter to J. Tyler of January 10, 1989; with a note in the hand of Dan H. Laurence near bottom of the sheet; original letter unlocated; begins "Dear Sir / I have written an article for you"
    - GBS: Autograph Letter Signed: to Augusta, Lady Gregory [initialed], July 26, 1917; postcard; 1 leaf (Box 12, Folder 37)
      London; begins "He literally was hovering over our chimney / pots with"